<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>go on Phil Pearl&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://philpearl.github.io/categories/go/</link>
    <description>Recent content in go on Phil Pearl&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://philpearl.github.io/categories/go/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Search for a new JSON: jsoniter</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/json_iter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/json_iter/</guid>
      <description>Both of my regular readers may be wondering what happened after my last blog about potentially forking encoding/json. Did I fork it? No I didn&amp;rsquo;t.
This is partly because I discovered https://github.com/json-iterator/go, which looks like it is the JSON library I was looking for. And partly because I spent my enthusiasm writing plenc - a serialisation library based around the protobuf wire protocol that bases message definitions on Go structures instead of .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining Evil</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/examining_evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/examining_evil/</guid>
      <description>It feels trite to write about the famous quote about premature optimisation being the root of all evil (I double-checked the definition of &amp;ldquo;trite&amp;rdquo; before I wrote that sentence!). But I do have a strongly-held opinion about it. What I like to call &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; levels of optimisation are not only not evil: they&amp;rsquo;re entirely necessary in many circumstances.
I keep hitting examples where performance was apparently not considered before something was released.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rebel Go: Forking encoding/json</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/json_own_way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/json_own_way/</guid>
      <description>So in my mind the conversation went a little like this.
Phil: I&amp;rsquo;d like to make encoding/json better. I&amp;rsquo;d like to save allocations when marshaling by adding a new interface for custom marshalers.
World: Given that this can be explored in 3rd-party packages easily, this seems like a likely decline. Leaving open for a week for final comments.
Phil: Oh, interesting, what would a successful exploration look like?
World: One consequence of writing your own package is that you could use it and would not need the change in the standard library.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Go: Contributing to encoding/json</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/json_good/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/json_good/</guid>
      <description>In my last post I whinged endlessly about encoding/json and in particular about the poor performance of anything with a custom marshaler. I decided to try to do something about it and I raised a proposal for a new marshaler interface.
As I half expected I wasn&amp;rsquo;t immediately welcomed as the new Go Messiah and my proposal has been effectively rejected (stop press - actually rejected). There&amp;rsquo;s very little inclination amongst the Go maintainers to change any of the interfaces in the standard libraries, and for some reason changing encoding/json or encoding/xml is viewed with particular horror.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bad Go: Adventures with JSON marshalling</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/badgo_json/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/badgo_json/</guid>
      <description>This is a story about encoding/json in the Go standard library. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to say this is bad Go. That would be heresy. But there is an aspect of marshalling that could be improved. Because it is in the standard library it isn&amp;rsquo;t bad Go, but if you followed the pattern in your own code then that would be a mistake. Outside of the standard library it would lose its magical aura, and it would be bad Go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bad Go: guessing</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_guessing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2019 09:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_guessing/</guid>
      <description>This is the 5th in a series of posts about Bad Go - a clickbaity title for posts about Go code that I&amp;rsquo;ve found frustrating because it could just be that little bit better. Better in my mind means more performant with less impact on GC, without being more complex or harder to read.
In this post I&amp;rsquo;ll rant about a problem I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in a number of blog posts. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it more in blog posts than in actual code, but I&amp;rsquo;m sure people do this with real coding too.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bad Go: not sizing slices</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_not_sizing_arrays/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 09:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_not_sizing_arrays/</guid>
      <description>This is the 4th in a series of posts about Bad Go - a clickbaity title for posts about Go code that I&amp;rsquo;ve found frustrating because it could just be that little bit better. Better in my mind means more performant with less impact on GC, without being more complex or harder to read.
In this post we&amp;rsquo;ll look at a very common issue - not setting the size of a slice when you know how big it needs to be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bad Go: frivolous Sprintf</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_sprintf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 09:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_sprintf/</guid>
      <description>This is the 3rd in a series of posts about Bad Go - a clickbaity title for posts about Go that I&amp;rsquo;ve found frustrating because it could just be that little bit better. Better in my mind is often more performant with less impact on GC without being more complex or harder to read.
The first two posts are about slices of pointers and pointer returns from functions
This one is about reaching for fmt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bad Go: pointer returns</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_pointer_returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_pointer_returns/</guid>
      <description>As an old C programmer I struggle with this one: it feels completely normal for functions to return pointers to structs. But I&amp;rsquo;ve a feeling this is bad Go, and that we&amp;rsquo;re normally better off returning struct values. I&amp;rsquo;m going to see if I can prove that returning struct values is just plain better, and that returning pointers is bad Go.
I&amp;rsquo;m going to define a struct that I can vary in size easily.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bad Go: slices of pointers</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_slice_of_pointers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 09:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bad_go_slice_of_pointers/</guid>
      <description>This is the first of what may be a series of blog posts on uses of Go that I&amp;rsquo;ve found frustrating. They&amp;rsquo;re mostly minor things that could just be better without being more complicated. I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to not only explain why they are bad but also demonstrate it.
First up is slices of pointers. Things like []*MyStruct. Unless you need to express that certain indices in the slice are nil, then this is just wasteful and []MyStruct is better in almost all circumstances.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go interfaces, but at what cost?</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/interface_at_what_cost/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 15:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/interface_at_what_cost/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s a cost associated with using interfaces. What is that cost? Let&amp;rsquo;s try and work out some of it.
Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the basic overhead of calling a method via an interface. We&amp;rsquo;ll define a very simple interface with a single method and a very simple implementation. We&amp;rsquo;ll also mark the method so it isn&amp;rsquo;t inlined by the compiler. We do this so that the call to get isn&amp;rsquo;t completely removed in the direct case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JSON and embedding</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/json_embed/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 20:49:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/json_embed/</guid>
      <description>Did everyone else already know this? Why didn&amp;rsquo;t you tell me? I got very confused the other day with some apparently simple JSON encoding. Here&amp;rsquo;s a simplified version, showing marshalling a struct with an embedded struct inside it.
package main import ( &amp;#34;encoding/json&amp;#34; &amp;#34;fmt&amp;#34; ) type Inner struct { InnerField string `json:&amp;#34;inner_field&amp;#34;` } type Outer struct { Inner OuterField string `json:&amp;#34;outer_field&amp;#34;` } func main() { val := Outer{ Inner: Inner { InnerField: &amp;#34;inner&amp;#34;, }, OuterField: &amp;#34;outer&amp;#34;, } data, err := json.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The why of Go strings</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/why_of_go_strings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 15:10:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/why_of_go_strings/</guid>
      <description>Regular readers of my blog will all be aware that in Go a string is in fact a struct with a pointer to an area of memory containing the byte content of the string and an integer Len that tells you how many bytes make up the string.
Ever wondered why? Probably not, as it seems “obvious” that you need both the length of the string and the bytes of the string to make a string.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further Dangers of Large Heaps in Go</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/danger_large_heap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 19:57:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/danger_large_heap/</guid>
      <description>The latest issue is a problem with the bulk feature extraction process we use at Ravelin (yes, we’re hiring! So if you like Go and you’re anywhere near London drop us a line). For our larger clients we’ve found this process just uses more and more memory, so we keep having to run it on more and more expensive boxes. I presumed it was a memory leak of some kind, so I decided to investigate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>bytes.Buffer revisited</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bytes_buffer_revisted/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Sep 2018 20:15:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/bytes_buffer_revisted/</guid>
      <description>Two years ago I wrote a post about building up strings with bytes.Buffer. I wondered what’s changed over the past two years?
Here are the benchmarks taken from the original post.
BenchmarkCopyKey-8 114 ns/op 31 B/op 1 allocs/op BenchmarkSimpleKey-8 141 ns/op 31 B/op 1 allocs/op BenchmarkSimpleMultilineKey-8 256 ns/op 63 B/op 4 allocs/op BenchmarkSprintfKey-8 392 ns/op 79 B/op 4 allocs/op BenchmarkJoinKey-8 156 ns/op 63 B/op 2 allocs/op BenchmarkBufferKey-8 268 ns/op 175 B/op 3 allocs/op BenchmarkSimpleBufferKey-8 265 ns/op 143 B/op 2 allocs/op If we run the same benchmarks with the latest version of Go — 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go in a scratch VM</title>
      <link>https://philpearl.github.io/post/go_scratch_vm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 20:19:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philpearl.github.io/post/go_scratch_vm/</guid>
      <description>Many of us know that you can run Go binaries in “scratch” containers. Your container doesn’t need to be based on Alpine or Ubuntu. It can be based on nothing and contain just the binary you built from Go source. This is largely because Go code can be statically linked, and so requires no installed libraries.
But what about VMs? Normally you start from Ubuntu, or Alpine or whatever and then you install your stuff on top.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>